Joan Gamell, Software Engineer

gamell [dot] works [at] proton [dot] me

(four one five) eight two five, two seven five eight



Technologist bred and fascinated by the web. Experienced in **full-stack development** but specialized in **front-end** in the recent years, loved building teams as a **manager** but **went back into coding as it is still his passion**. Thrives in roles with a **mix of technical and leadership** responsibilities. Continuous improvement is his chief principle.

Professional Experience

Staff Software Engineer (Front End) at Slack in San Francisco, September 2018 - Present

Slack - where work happens ™

Matured as a well-rounded Front End Staff Engineer leading engineering in mission-critical projects, designing test framework architecture and working in the foundational front end infrastructure that underpins the whole Slack client & webapps.

- Helped ship the **Shared Channels** feature (later known as Slack Connect, where organizations can connect with each other) & subsequently lead numerous front-end projects between 2019-2022 which helped **grow the SC Network from 0 to thousands of organizations**.
- Lead the development of the initial Slack Connect invite / acceptance / approval flow experience using React & Redux.
- Architected highly complex go-to-market deployment strategies as our product was actively used by hundreds of enterprise organizations.
- Was the main liasion between engineering, product and design, **performing TPM-like tasks** clarifying requirements, managing deadlines and encouraing a team culture where all functions build the product together iteratively.
- Performed extensive code refactorings to improve typing of crucial domain entities used throughout the codebase in order to remove escape hatches that render type-checking useless.
- Implemented **developer experience improvements** through linters (eslint), tests and codemods to improve the front end codebase at scale and nudge engineers to keep following the best practices.
- · Coached and mentored engineers, helping them develop their technical skills and professional career.
- Lead **initiatives to improve and optimize processes** used in the Software Development & Product Development Lifecycles, resulting in more iterative and agile aproaches to building software.
- Deeply **improved the systems & processes around the test framework** used by all engineers and quality engineers to write E2E tests, greatly improving its adoption and ease of use.

Staff Software Engineer at LinkedIn in San Francisco, May 2017 - September 2018

LinkedIn is the largest professional network site with more then 500M AU

Went back to being an Individual Contributor to focus on my tech skills by joining the front-end team in charge of building the portal to setup and manage advertising campaigns within LinkedIn.

- Lead a project to migrate existing integration tests to a new and better custom-built framework built with Scala, Java and Selenium.
- · On-boarded dozens of engineers onto the new framework by holding on-boarding sessions, extensive code pairing and code reviewing.
- · Owned the CI/CD pipeline and increased its quality and reliability.
- Assumed the Tech Lead role in a project to migrate the app's UI to Ember. The role entailed being the point person for that part of the project, translating product requirements into actionable tasks, planning and estimation, helping with technical designs and making sure our quality standards are upheld in the code.
- · Mentored numerous team members.

Engineering Manager at Expedia in San Francisco, Jul 2015 - May 2017

Expedia is one of the world's largest Online Travel Agent (OTA)

Having hands-on technical skills in this managerial position was critical to scaling and leading an energetic team of engineers who owned the whole stack and deployed to production daily following Continuous Deployment practices.

- Built and led a successful team of engineers who owned the complete Product & Tech Stack and reliably delivered according to Product's
 expectations.
- Lead the engineering team to generate a projected \$70M+ of Gross Profit in 2016.
- Scaled the team several times from 4 to 16 members in 2 years while minimizing impact on sprint velocity and deliverables.
- Overcame the challenges of leading a distributed team across 4 locations in 2 different timezones and adjusted the team's processes for
 optimal performance in this remote configuration.
- Achieved zero outstanding bugs several months by ensuring quality is built-in and automated in the code and pipeline and by continuously
 performing preventive maintenance.
- Mentored and coached team members, empowering them to take decisions and to continuously improve themselves through data and feedback, and worked through performance issues with team members when needed.
- · Laid out the technical vision for the product, liaised and collaborated with other teams to achieve our goals.
- Helped deliver the official Expedia Alexa Skill under a tight deadline as a side project. The project was developed using node, AWS lambda and Dynamo DB.

- Developed and open-sourced a library to functionally test Alexa Skills.
- Wrote code, paired coded, performed code reviews and helped debug issues. Fluent in: JavaScript, HTML, CSS and Java.

Tech Lead at Expedia in San Francisco, Oct 2014 - Jul 2015

First role with people manager responsibilities in a small team of engineers where we owned the whole tech stack for the product.

- Led the effort to scale the system to serve x5 more requests with the same team.
- Performed as main project point person and liaison with other teams and Product stakeholders.
- Assumed the de-facto role of a Technical Project Manager / Delivery Manager and perfected the team's semi-kanban process.
- · Hired, on-boarded and mentored new team members.
- · Headed front-end development in the team, using mainly vanilla JS, LESS/CSS, HTML and node.
- Estimated new feature effort levels and worked with Product on Backlog planning/grooming.

Front-end Engineer at Expedia in Singapore, Oct 2012 - Oct 2014

Main front-end developer of a fully-responsive, high-traffic, highly-available e-commerce website: AirAsiaGo. Used Kanban & Continuous Deployment methodologies and followed Clean Code practices.

- Developed, tested and shipped cross-browser, responsive, retina-ready features and modules built with HTML5, JavaScript jQuery, Backbone, AngularJS etc CSS3 (LESS), SVG, sprites, etc. on top of a Spring (Java) back-end.
- Led the team's front-end vision and development. Evangelize best practices by mentoring team mates.
- Interacted with UI Design team, providing constant feedback on the difficulty/feasibility of the planned features.
- Optimized page load-time and SEO ranking through minification, caching, selective loading, changes in front-end architecture, usage of subdomain-per-asset CDNs, sprite and image compression, etc.
- Identified, debugged and fixed live-site issues within hours (Splunk, Nagios, AWS monitoring, Google Analytics, etc.).

Sr Web Developer & Tech Lead at Optimum Solutions (for SC Bank) in Singapore, Jan - Oct 2012

Optimum Solutions is a Singaporean mid-size IT consultant company. SCB is a global bank with branches in 70 countries over 80,000 employees

Worked on the RMWB (Relation Manager WorkBench) project for Standard Chartered Bank. Was responsible of developing and shipping the front-end of the application the corporate customers would use.

Analyst at BBVA in Madrid, Sep 2010 - Dec 2011

BBVA is the second-largest Spanish bank with more than 100,000 employees around the world

Worked on the *Mentor* project at Wholesale Banking & Asset Management, Global Risk Unit. Designed and implemented the whole UI layer with JSP, HTML and JavaScript (jQuery, Ajax, async plugin loading).

Developer at Safelayer Secure Communications in Barcelona, Feb 2009 - Sep 2010

Safelayer is a mid-size, Spanish IT security company

Invented, designed and implemented a proof of concept of *gOTP*, a novel two-factor authentication system which combined the robustness of One Time Passwords and the easily-remembered Graphical Passwords.

Education

Informatics Engineering, 2004-2009 at Barcelona School of Informatics (FIB), UPC, Barcelona (Spain)

BSc + MSc Graduated with Honors in the Final Degree Project "A Secure Authentication System via OTP and Graphical Password"

Other courses

Startup Engineering, 2013 at Coursera (Stanford University) | Spring Training, 2011 at SpringSource University | iPhone Application Programming, 2009 at iTunesU (Stanford University)

Additional Information

- Languages: Native Spanish and Catalan speaker. Full Proficiency of English.
- Photography: Have won prizes, had pictures featured in several editorials (e.g. 500px editors choice) and contributed thousands of dollars to charity by auctioning my pictures. My portfolio
- . Traveling: Have traveled to more than 35 countries and always thinking where to go next.